Preparation for communication is absolutely critical,
but it’s often the most neglected part of it.
So what is EPIC? EPIC is a communication framework — four elements to it. It’s very intuitive,
very easy to remember, but it packs a really mighty punch.
The E in EPIC stands for Empathy.
Before you can chart a course with somebody,
before you can map out how you’re going to get from where they are now to where you need them to be,
you need to have a really good understanding of where they are.
Not just who they are — that’s important, of course —
but where they are in terms of their feelings, their understanding,
their attitudes, their behaviours to your topic;
what pressures might your audience be facing, both professionally and, in many cases, personally?
Think about what’s going on in their lives and how that might affect
the way they react and respond to you.
— And I think important here is making no assumptions.
It’s really thinking about what you know about the audience and what they care about.
And once we’ve thought about Empathy, we can then think about Purpose, the P of EPIC.
And by purpose we mean…
the objective of the meeting.
Well, for truly impactful communication you need to do more than that.
You need to have a clear sense of where you’re going to end up
at the end of the meeting, the presentation, whatever the interaction is.
And once we’ve thought about Empathy and Purpose, then we think about what we’re going to present at the meeting, or what we’re going to show.
And this is the I of EPIC, which stands for Insight.
Insight is really all the knowledge and analysis and benchmarking — whatever information you have — that has
prompted you to have this meeting, or be called to this meeting, in the first place.
The question to ask yourself here
is: what insights will serve your purpose?
What insights will achieve your purpose in the meeting?
Now, you’ve been asked to this meeting because you know a lot about the topic.
If communication is more art than science,
then it’s more sculpture than painting.
In painting, you’re adding to build your picture;
in sculpting, you’re chipping away.
And when you’re deciding on the insights to use, you’re chipping away at everything you have
to reveal the core key insights that will best achieve your purpose.
And then finally, the C of EPIC is Conversation.
And this is really thinking about how you are going to run the discussion.
How will you open it? How will you close the discussion?
What roles will people play in the meeting? How might you answer questions people have?
And what kind of tone do you want to start and finish on?
Whether you’re giving a presentation to a couple of hundred people in an auditorium,
whether you’re having a one-on-one, or whether you’re presenting to your executive committee,
it’s about conversation.
It’s also thinking about how you will interact with the audience.
It’s called conversation, not monologue, for a reason.
How do you prompt questions?
How do you get the audience involved in your content?
The EPIC worksheet lays out the questions to ask yourself as you’re preparing.
If you use EPIC to plan the last few feet of your journey,
then your communication can ensure that what you’ve been working on
can have the impact that it needs to have.